<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: finances | Neflaria Development Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://Olivine-Labs.github.com/Neflaria-Blog/blog/categories/finances/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Olivine-Labs.github.com/Neflaria-Blog/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-14T12:26:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://Olivine-Labs.github.com/Neflaria-Blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Olivine Labs]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[projects@olivinelabs.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Rise of the Shadow Empire: The Next Age of Neflaria]]></title>
    <link href="http://Olivine-Labs.github.com/Neflaria-Blog/blog/2012/01/19/the-rise-of-the-shadow-empire-the-next-age-of-neflaria/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-19T10:46:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://Olivine-Labs.github.com/Neflaria-Blog/blog/2012/01/19/the-rise-of-the-shadow-empire-the-next-age-of-neflaria</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/uedLr.jpg" alt="We can rebuild him. We have the technology." /></p>

<p>It's always been our goal- at least, for the last several years- to rebuild
Neflaria with a goal of flexibility (to add new features) and maintainability
(to fix bugs.) The current codebase is pretty old and cumbersome; it has
hindered us trying to add new features and fix existing bugs, and it's kept us
from moving forward and growing the game as we know Neflaria can.</p>

<p>Let's talk about where Neflaria's going, and what we're doing with our donations.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The problem with doing that is time; we need to make sure that we can keep
content fresh (with, for example, the Age of Quiesence and Shattered Tranquility
updates) and maintain the current game state, juggle moderation and normal
day-to-day operations, <em>and</em> find time to rebuild the game. It's difficult to
take the couple months it might take to rebuild the game without parts of the
live game falling apart.</p>

<p>Thanks to our amazing players, however, we've been able to raise enough funding
to get some help. We want to be transparent about how much we've made and what
we're doing with the money- we are calling them <em>donations</em>, after all, not sales.
Here's the breakdown:</p>

<ul>
<li>We averaged about $2,000 / month in donations from August - December;
on track for averaging $1,000 in January</li>
<li>Server costs: 6 webservers, loadbalancing, and large high-CPU database:
~$560/mo, depending on load.</li>
<li>We spent about $400 in advertising (banners, setting up a Neflaria store, etc.)</li>
<li>We spent about $400 on training (developent books, courses, etc.)</li>
<li>We spent about $1500 on software licenses (source control (Github), Photoshop,
tracking software, etc.)</li>
</ul>


<p>From August - December, we made about $11,000; of that, we spent around $5,000
between servers, software, and increasing development efficiency, leaving $6,000
left over.</p>

<p>We also spent a significant portion of our time building a new web development
framework, <a href="https://github.com/Olivine-Labs/Mint">Mint</a>,
and we're putting together a gaming platform that we can build
Neflaria on. We're open-sourcing much of the software we
create so that we can give it back to the community; we've also built other
systems that we have or are in the process of open-sourcing.</p>

<p><span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='what would take us <em>weeks</em> to do now will shorten to <em>days</em> '>
The money we have left over combined with  the work we've done on our
framework leaves us at a place where we can hire a freelancer or two to build
Neflaria the way it should be, using modern technology that we've built, so
that we can grow, add new features, and upgrade the game.  The quantifiable
difference is massive;
what would take us <em>weeks</em> to do now will shorten to <em>days</em>
in this new system that we've architected. The system will also be more
server-efficient, so that we can reduce some of our server costs and at the
same time handle more players. We've signed a contract for just under $6,000
to develop Neflaria on this new platform, and we expect work to start in the
next week.
</span></p>

<p>In the meantime, the donations we receive will go back into the bank; we need
to rebuild our savings a bit so that we can prepare to scale up the servers
and invest in the platform that will be running Neflaria.</p>

<p>Look out for the next blog post that will talk about what new features will be
in The Rise of the Shadow Empire! We've got some really cool things coming up
that we're excited to share with you and get your feedback on. We'll also
discuss a planned, regular update schedule and talk about what's going on with
resets.</p>

<p>edit: Can't get away without giving you a hint: realtime chat and the mystery
socket is involved</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
